Finding Aid for Merrill M. Flood Papers
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Merrill M. Flood Papers 1930-1991, 1943-1990
Flood, Merrill Meeks, 1908-
1 linear feet
9757 Aa 2
Mathematician, student of John Von Neumann, specializing in applied mathematics and game theory and decision making theory, director of several research laboratories, including Willow Run at the University of Michigan. Papers include, research notes, publications, correspondence and other material relating to his research and professional activities.
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection (Donor No. 8491 ) was received from Carla Wren in November 1996.
The collection is open for research.
Merrill M. Flood devoted his career to researching applied mathematics and organizational theory. He advised a wide variety of public and private organizations on how to apply mathematical principles to practical situations and social interactions. Flood was born in Seward, Nebraska on November 28, 1908. He received a bachelor's degree from the University of Nebraska in 1933, and a master's degree in mathematics from the same institution in 1930. In 1935, Flood earned a Ph.D. in mathematics from Princeton University.
At Princeton, Flood began his career as a consultant and researcher, advising state and local government organizations in New Jersey and elsewhere. From 1942 to 1949, Flood owned and operated a consulting firm, advising government agencies on national defense technology, primarily aerial surveillance and mapping instruments. From 1949 to 1952, Flood worked as a Project Officer for Logistics at the RAND Corporation. At RAND, Flood worked under his former teacher, John von Neumann, conducting pioneering research into game theory, which strongly influenced the government's nuclear strategy during the Cold War.
In 1953, Flood returned to academia as director of the Institute for Research in the Management of Industrial Production at Columbia University. In 1956, Flood accepted his first appointment at the University of Michigan, as head of Willow Run Laboratories (predecessor of the Environmental Research Institute of Michigan). During his three-year tenure at Willow Run, Flood continued his research into combat surveillance systems as supervisor of Project Michigan. Flood also accepted other university appointments: professor of Industrial Engineering in 1956, senior research mathematician at the Mental Health Research Institute in 1959, and professor of mathematical biology in the Department of Psychiatry, also in 1959. From 1959 until his retirement from the university in 1967, he researched learning models, adaptive systems, and information storage and retrieval networks. After several years of consulting for business and government organizations, Flood returned to Ann Arbor in 1974 for a three-year appointment as a professor of education and director of the Faculty Research Program on University Governance, where he continued his investigation of decision-making and organization theory. After his appointment as professor emeritus in 1977, Flood continued his research at Stanford University, the University of Louisville, and, finally, the University of California at San Diego. Flood died in La Jolla, California on March 24, 1991.
Merrill Flood's papers are arranged into five series. A small Biographical File contains curricula vitae (1966 and 1974) and news clippings from the University of Michigan News and Information Service. Also included is a bibliography of nearly three hundred published and unpublished research papers which Flood produced between 1930 and 1976.
The Correspondence Series (1938-1990) is arranged chronologically and consists of five folders related to Flood's research during the 1940s and the 1980s, with little material from the intervening years. Correspondence relating to Flood's work with the Faculty Program on University Governance has been interfiled with the related research reports.
A small Publications File (1937-1984, n.d.) contains twelve journal articles relating to the full range of Flood's research interests. Most of Flood's Research Notes (1929-1967, scattered) were unlabeled and undated. One file of notes, better labeled than most and dating largely from the late 1950s to early 1960s, has been retained in its original order.
The bulk of the material in the Flood collection is contained in the series, Reports and Drafts (1930-1981, n.d.), arranged chronologically. The series begins with two papers from the late 1930s on local government in New Jersey, followed by consultation research reports from the 1940s on optical systems, aerial combat surveillance, and aerial mapping. From the early 1950s, the series contains several reports on game theory and decision-making written for the RAND Corporation. Three papers relating to management science resulted from Flood's work at Columbia University in the mid-1950s. The series also consists of numerous reports documenting Flood's appointments at the University of Michigan. His work with the Mental Health Research Institute is represented in several research papers on learning theory and information processing networks. The other substantive section of this series consists of six working papers, with related correspondence, on decision-making and organization theory, resulting from Flood's 1970s work with the Faculty Research Program on University Governance. Reports from 1943, 1962, 1967 and 1973 derive from Flood's consultation work on behalf of private organizations.
This collection does not document Flood's work as Head of Willow Run Laboratories. For information on this period, researchers should consult the record group University of Michigan Division of Research Development and Administration.
The Merrill Flood papers are divided into the following five series:
Biographical File, 1959-1991
Correspondence, 1938-1990
Publications File, 1937-1984, n.d.
Reports and Drafts, 1930-1981, n.d.
Research Notes, 1929-1967
Subjects:
Floor, Merrill Meeks, 1908-; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Mental Health Research Institute.; University of Michigan. Faculty Research Program on University Governance.; Rand Corporation.; Organization--Research.; Decision-making, Group.; Aerial observation (Military Science); Game theory.; Aerial photogrammetry.; Operations research.
- Biographical File 1959-1991
  The Biographical File series contains curricula vitae (1966 and 1974) and news clippings from the University of Michigan News and Information Service. Also included is a bibliography of nearly three hundred published and unpublished research papers which Flood produced between 1930 and 1976.
  - 1959-1991 (Box 1)
- Correspondence 1938-1990
  The correspondence series is arranged chronologically and consists of five folders related to Merrill Flood's research during the 1940s and the 1980s, with little material from the intervening years. Correspondence relating to Flood's work with the Faculty Program on University Governance has been interfiled with the related research reports.
  - Mendel, Clifford, 1938-1946 (Box 1)
  - Classes, 1942-1946 (Box 1)
  - Leon, Alberto, 1963 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - 1947-1987 (Box 1)
      (scattered)
    - 1987-1990 (Box 1)
- Publications File 1937-1984, n.d.
  The publications series contains twelve journal articles relating to the full range of Flood's research interests.
  - 1937-1984, n.d. (Box 1)
- Reports and Drafts 1930-1981, n.d.
  The bulk of the material in the Merrill Flood collection is contained in the reports and drafts series and is arranged chronologically. The series begins with two papers from the late 1930s on local government in New Jersey, followed by consultation research reports from the 1940s on optical systems, aerial combat surveillance, and aerial mapping. From the early 1950s, the series contains several reports on game theory and decision-making written for the RAND Corporation. Three papers relating to management science resulted from Flood's work at Columbia University in the mid-1950s. The series also consists of numerous reports documenting Flood's appointments at the University of Michigan. His work with the Mental Health Research Institute is represented in several research papers on learning theory and information processing networks. The other substantive section of this series consists of six working papers, with related correspondence, on decision-making and organization theory, resulting from Flood's 1970s work with the Faculty Research Program on University Governance. Reports from 1943, 1962, 1967 and 1973 derive from Flood's consultation work on behalf of private organizations.
  This collection does not document Flood's work as Head of Willow Run Laboratories. For information on this period, researchers should consult the record group University of Michigan Division of Research Development and Administration.
  - "Forms of Primes Having a Given Number As a Quadratic Resolution" (University of Nebraska Master's Thesis) 1930 (Box 1)
  - "Measuring Local Government" 1937 (Box 1)
  - "Winning Games of Chance" 1939 (Box 1)
  - "Semi-Annual Reports to Aero Service Corporation" 1943 (Box 1)
  - Report to American Geographical Society on Miller Stereoscopic Mapping Instrument 1943 (Box 1)
  - Reports to National Defense Research Committee on Optical Instruments and Aerial Surveillance 1943-44 (Box 1)
  - Progress Reports to National Defense Research Committee, 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - "Mapping Studies" 1943-1944 (Box 1)
  - Report on Pacific Fleet Conditions Regarding Photogrammetric Equipment 1944 (Box 1)
  - Memorandum to Harvard School of Education 1946 (Box 1)
  - "Preference Experiment Papers" (RAND) 1951 (Box 1)
  - "Some Experimental Games" (RAND) 1952 (Box 1)
  - "Aerial Bombing Tactics: General Considerations" (RAND) 1952 (Box 1)
  - "The Influence of Environmental Non-Stationary in a Sequential Decision-Making Experiment" (RAND) 1952 (Box 1)
  - "On Game-Learning Theory and Some Decision-Making Experiments" (RAND) 1952 (Box 1)
  - Minutes of University Seminar on Labor 1955 (Box 1)
  - Presidential Address at Meeting of the Institute for Management Sciences, 1955 (Box 1)
  - "New Mathematical Tools for Decision-Making" 1956 (Box 1)
  - Seven Reports, on Learning Models, Adaptive Systems, and Information Networks, from the Mental Health Research Institute 1959-1967 (Box 1)
  - "A Group Interaction Experiment" 1963 (Box 1)
  - Report for Communications Workers of America on Public Broadcasting 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Information System Value" 1967 (Box 1)
  - "Optimization of Steady State Pipeline Networks" 1973 (Box 1)
  - Six Working Papers and Related Correspondence, on Decision-Making Models, from the Faculty Research Program on University Governance 1974-1981, n.d. (Box 1)
  - "Game-by-Game Predictions in Chess Matches" circa 1980 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Reports on Decision-Making and Organization Theory Undated (Box 1)
  - "Some Problems in the Analysis of Consecutive Measurements" Undated (Box 1)
- Research Notes 1929-1967
  Most of Flood's research notes were unlabeled and undated. One file of notes, better labeled than most and dating largely from the late 1950s to early 1960s, has been retained in its original order.
  - 1929-1967 (Box 1)